In this segment we will talk about how to set your tent up in the snow.
In the coldest part of the winter you are certainly going to want a four season tent.
You can use a three season tent towards either end of the season.
If you are using a three season tent it is a good idea to use a ground cloth.
You will want to set your door so that it is facing your gear that makes the shortest trip between the door and your gear when you need it for convenience sake.
This tent has two doors so we won't have to consider that.
If you weren't able to get the ground perfectly flat which is often the case you will want to consider where to put your head.
It is a good idea for the head end of the tent, where that is where you are going to be laying your head when you are sleeping to be on the higher ground.
You will sleep better that way.
Now hopefully what you did before you came out here was set your tent at home so that you know for sure how it sets up and that you have all the pieces that you need.
This will save you a lot of grief and also be a really good way of knowing that you can set your tent up faster especially as the sun sets and it is getting cold and you would like to get that tent up.
I am using snow stakes which have a little better purchase on the snow and will hold the tent a little more securely than the wire stakes that normally come with your tent.
If once you set your tent you don't feel that it is still secure enough you can always try to find l rocks or large quantities of snow to set over the stakes to help anchor them in.
When you are pouring out all the parts to your tent they can get lost pretty easily in the snow, particularly if it is fresh powder so it is a good idea to lay down some kind of a cloth that all your stakes and miscellaneous pieces go on otherwise you will be digging for them or worse yet not be able to set your tent.
I have found a couple of rocks that I can put over the stakes and that may be good enough but I'm going to go a step further and cover them with snow to sort of anchor them in place and that should keep my stakes where they belong and my tent standing through the night.
Now the final step of course is to put your rain fly in.
You will stake it out the same way and that will give you a secure tent that you will be able to rely on for the night.